and finally let's talk about raid 5.
which uses a technique called
distributed block interleaved parity to
protect the disks
it does block interleaved parity just
like grade 4 but its parity is not all
on the same disk it is spread among all
the disks so when we have four disks the
first set of stripes in raid 5 will be
exactly the same as in raid 4. there
will be three stripes of data on the
first three disks and the parity for
these three stripes which is computed by
xoring the data bit by bit
in the three stripes and the resulting
parity stripe is written to the fourth
disk but raid 4 would do the same thing
and put the next parity here as well in
contrast rate 5 puts the next parity
stripe not here
but on the next disk so we get three
data stripes on these disks now and
their parity is here then for the next
set of stripes we again move the parity
to another disk and then for the next
set of Stripes the parity moves again
and then for the next set of Stripes the
parity would again be here and so on so
as you can see the blocked interleaved
parity what it really does is it gets
the parity here and then here
and then here
and then here and then again here so
each of the disks will get its fair
share of parity but for each set of
stripes we will have three stripes in
this case and the parity block is just
that the next set of four will have a
parity in a different place so what we
get is the read performance where all
four discs can actually be used for
reading data and we get n times the
throughput of one disk remember that
raid 4 was getting n minus 1 times the
throughput of one disk because one of
the disks was not used for data here the
data is spread over all four disks so
chances are of all the blocks we want to
read they will be equally distributed
among the four disks in this case
right performance
is still affected by having to read and
then write the data and the parity
so a single right results in four axises
if you remember we would read
the data block and the parity and then
we would write the data block and the
parity so there are four axises per
right but they are distributed among all
the disks so we get n over 4 times the
throughput of one disk in this case we
have four disks so right performance is
equal to the throughput of one of the
disks if it was used without rate
remember that in raid 4 a write
performance is always limited to half
the throughput of one disk
in this case
it would be half of the performance of
one disk versus the full performance of
one disk so we win if we had for example
eight disks here we will get twice the
throughput of one disk with raid 4 the 8
discs would still have a single parity
disk and the right performance would
still be half the throughput of that one
disk
and the reliability of raid 5
is the same as raid 4. this fails if we
lose more than one disk just like in
raid 4 in any group of four Stripes here
we could lose one of the disks if we
lose the parity disk we can still read
everything and write if we lose a data
disk we can reconstruct the data using
the parity
here any one of the disks played the
role of a data disk in some group of
stripes and play the role of a parity
disk in some groups of stripes
so all groups of stripes are still
usable after we lose only one disk if we
lose two disks however then we have a
problem